♪Chasing wind, I set out afar♪
♪ Habol ng hangin, nagtakda ako ng malayo ♪
♪The road ahead lost, my voice unheard♪
♪The road ahead lost, my voice unheard♪
♪I've tasted joy and sorrow♪
♪ Natikman ko ang kagalakan at kalungkutan ♪
♪Laying low, I plan every move♪
♪Laying low, I plan every move♪
♪With a mortal heart and lingering ties♪
♪ na may isang mortal na puso at matagal na ugnayan ♪
♪I'm roaming far and wide♪
♪I am roaming far and wide♪
♪A twist of fate in desperate times♪
♪ Isang twist ng kapalaran sa mga desperadong oras ♪
♪A bond that outlives the dust of life♪
♪A bond that outlives the dust of life♪
♪Still chasing what immortality means♪
♪ Habol pa rin kung ano ang ibig sabihin ng imortalidad ♪
♪Even eternity flashes by in a blink♪
♪Even eternity flashes by in a blink♪
♪Don't mock my ordinary life♪
♪ Huwag mo ang aking ordinaryong buhay ♪
♪I fight alone as chaos shakes the world♪
♪I fight alone as chaos shakes the world♪
♪Don't scorn my humble roots♪
♪ Huwag hurso ang aking mapagpakumbabang ugat ♪
♪Kind at heart, ruthless when I must be♪
♪Kind at heart, ruthless when I must be♪
♪Fate stirs with joy and grief beneath♪
♪ Ang kapalaran ay gumagalaw sa kagalakan at kalungkutan sa ilalim ng ♪
♪I hold the tide between life and death♪
♪I hold the tide between life and death♪
♪Faith carries me through endless dark♪
♪ Ang pananampalataya ay nagdadala sa akin sa pamamagitan ng walang katapusang madilim ♪
♪And I return with a heart refined♪
♪And I return with a heart refined♪
♪Forged by trial, I rise through three realms♪
♪ Forged by Trial, tumaas ako sa tatlong realms ♪
♪Reborn in the wheel of fate♪
♪Reborn in the wheel of fate♪
[The Immortal Ascension]
[Ang walang kamatayang pag -akyat]
[Adapted from the webnovel, The Immortal Ascension by Wangyu]
[Adapted from the webnovel, The Immortal Ascension by Wangyu]
[serialized in www.qidian.com under China Literature Limited]
[Serialized sa www.qidian.com sa ilalim ng China Literature Limited]
[Episode 26]
[Episode 26]
Qu Hun,
Qu hun,
where are you?
Nasaan ka?
♪Shards of dreams inside a dream♪
♪Shards of dreams inside a dream♪
♪A pale moon falls into mirrored skies♪
♪ Ang isang maputlang buwan ay nahuhulog sa mirrored kalangitan ♪
♪Years slipped by as I lingered on♪
♪Years slipped by as I lingered on♪
♪Old scenes rise again...♪
♪ Tumataas muli ang mga lumang eksena... ♪
Found you.
Found you.
♪They say the past fades like smoke♪
♪ Sinasabi nila ang nakaraan na nawawala tulad ng usok ♪
♪But looking back still stirs the ache♪
♪But looking back still stirs the ache♪
♪This noisy world, this lonely page♪
♪ Ang maingay na mundo na ito, ang malungkot na pahina na ito
♪Swept away by time♪
♪Swept away by time♪
♪Eyes once looked far, now lost in the shift...♪
♪ Ang mga mata minsan ay tumingin sa malayo, ngayon nawala sa shift... ♪
Why?
Why?
Why is spiritual power
Bakit ang espirituwal na kapangyarihan mula sa Tier 5 o
from the Tier 5 or Tier 6 of the Qi Refining Stage radiating from him?
Tier 6 ng Qi Refining Stage na nagliliwanag mula sa kanya?
Zhang Tie,
Zhang Tie,
is that you?
Ikaw ba yun?
Have you come back?
Have you come back?
Blockhead!
Blockhead!
Where have you been?
Nasaan ka na?
♪Time will fade♪
♪Time will fade♪
♪All the words ever spoken♪
♪ Lahat ng mga salitang sinasalita ♪
♪Only this longing remains♪
♪Only this longing remains♪
♪Crossing centuries and days...♪
♪ Tumawid ng mga siglo at araw... ♪
Is this real?
Is this real?
Zhang Tie,
Zhang Tie,
is it really you?
is it really you?
Have you come back?
Bumalik ka na ba?
Father!
Father!
Come here, darling.
Come here, darling.
Good girl.
Magandang babae.
Is that medicine for your mother?
Is that medicine for your mother?
- She fell asleep after lunch. - Good girl.
- Nakatulog siya pagkatapos ng tanghalian.  - Good girl.
Is that so?
Ganun ba?
He's not Zhang Tie.
He is not Zhang Tie.
Who is he?
Sino siya?
You're certainly good at playing the part.
You are certainly good at playing the part.
Who are you?
Sino ka?
That's my question.
Iyon ang tanong ko.
I don't understand what you're saying.
I do not understand what you are saying.
Is that so?
Ganun ba?
You've taken someone else's body.
You have taken someone else's body.
That woman and child
Ang babaeng iyon at anak
aren't yours either.
aren't yours either.
So, I'll ask you again.
Kaya, tatanungin kita ulit.
Who are you?
Who are you?
You know me?
Kilala mo ako?
To be honest with you,
To be honest with you,
I've forgotten everything
Nakalimutan ko na ang lahat
since I fell off that cliff five years ago.
since I fell off that cliff five years ago.
I don't remember my name,
Hindi ko naaalala ang pangalan ko,
or why I'm here.
or why I am here.
But I keep hearing a friend calling out to me.
Ngunit patuloy kong naririnig ang isang kaibigan na tumatawag sa akin.
Over and over, he calls my name,
Over and over, he calls my name,
yet I just can't remember.
Ngunit hindi ko lang maalala.
There's something important I must have forgotten.
There's something important I must have forgotten.
Why?
Bakit?
Why can't I remember?
Why can't I remember?
I just can't seem to recall…
I just can't seem to recall…
Zhang Tie,
Zhang Tie,
don't be like this.
do not be like this.
It's not your fault.
Hindi mo ito kasalanan.
Zhang Tie?
Zhang Tie?
My name is Zhang Tie?
Ang pangalan ko ay Zhang Tie?
You really aren't Zhang Tie.
You really aren't Zhang Tie.
There's no way you could be.
Walang paraan na maaari kang maging.
Though, you are very much like him.
Though, you are very much like him.
Watching you eat,
Pinapanood kang kumain,
work the forge,
work the forge,
even the way you talk…
Kahit na ang paraan ng pag -uusap mo...
I almost believed
I almost believed
he had come back.
Bumalik na siya.
But a person's eyes
But a person's eyes
never lie.
Huwag kailanman magsinungaling.
Yours are cold and calculating.
Yours are cold and calculating.
You couldn't possibly be him.
Hindi ka maaaring maging kanya.
So what?
So what?
Why does it matter to you?
Bakit mahalaga sa iyo?
His life-bound artifact
His life-bound artifact
is with you?
ay kasama mo?
This body isn't yours.
This body isn't yours.
Get out of it!
Lumabas ka rito!
Dear,
Dear,
what's going on?
Ano ang nangyayari?
Father.
Father.
Did you hear something?
May narinig ka ba?
There was a stray cat
Nagkaroon ng isang naliligaw na
sneaking up on our duckling.
pusa na nag -sneaking sa aming pato.
We chased it away.
We chased it away.
Dear.
Mahal.
And who is our guest?
And who is our guest?
He's a friend
Kaibigan siya
who came looking for me.
who came looking for me.
Kept insisting I make him a new set of weapons.
Patuloy na iginiit na ginagawa ko siyang isang bagong hanay ng mga armas.
I've already turned him down several times.
I have already turned him down several times.
That's right.
Tama yan.
I hope I didn't disturb you,
I hope I didn't disturb you,
Ma'am.
Ma'am.
Not at all.
Not at all.
Please, come in.
Mangyaring, pumasok.
No need.
No need.
We'll just have a quick word,
Magkakaroon lang kami ng isang mabilis
then I'll be on my way.
na salita, pagkatapos ay papunta na ako.
Yue, help your mother back to her room.
Yue, help your mother back to her room.
Close the door. It's windy.
Isara ang pinto.  It is windy.
Go on.
Magpatuloy ka na
- Hurry. - Go on.
- Hurry.  - magpatuloy.
Go inside.
Go inside.
Speak.
Magsalita.
Who are you?
Who are you?
If you tell the truth,
Kung sasabihin mo ang totoo,
I promise I won't harm them.
I promise I will not harm them.
But if you lie,
Ngunit kung nagsisinungaling ka,
well, you can try me.
well, you can try me.
I was injured
Nasugatan ako
in a battle against an enemy.
in a battle against an enemy.
I was desperate and took this body.
Desperado ako at kinuha ang katawan na ito.
I had no choice.
I had no choice.
Please forgive me.
Patawarin mo ako.
At least that sounds reasonable.
At least that sounds reasonable.
Which sect are you from?
Saang sekta ka galing?
I'm from Spirit Beast Mountain.
I am from Spirit Beast Mountain.
Are you also
Ikaw din
with the Seven Sects?
with the Seven Sects?
Oh, you're from the Spirit Beast Mountain.
Oh, ikaw ay mula sa bundok ng hayop na hayop.
How's your Senior Zhong Wu doing?
How's your Senior Zhong Wu doing?
You know Senior Zhong Wu?
Alam mo ang senior zhong wu?
That's good to hear.
That is good to hear.
Looks like we're all acquainted.
Mukhang lahat tayo ay pamilyar.
Yes.
Yes.
All acquaintances.
Lahat ng kakilala.
Zhong Wu cut ties with Spirit Beast Mountain a long time ago.
Zhong Wu cut ties with Spirit Beast Mountain a long time ago.
Still not ready to tell the truth?
Hindi pa rin handa na sabihin ang totoo?
I'll talk!
I will talk!
I'll talk.
Mag -uusap ako.
I'm a disciple
Ako ay isang alagad
of the Beast Taming Sect under the Tiandu Kingdom.
of the Beast Taming Sect under the Tiandu Kingdom.
The Six Demonic Sects?
Ang anim na demonyong sekta?
Yes.
Yes.
Years ago,
Taon na ang nakalilipas,
I fought someone here
I fought someone here
and was seriously injured.
at malubhang nasugatan.
My body was destroyed,
My body was destroyed,
and in desperation,
at sa desperasyon,
I let my primordial spirit leave the body.
I let my primordial spirit leave the body.
Just when I had lost all hope,
Kapag nawalan ako ng lahat ng pag -asa,
I found this empty vessel without a soul.
I found this empty vessel without a soul.
But
Ngunit
after entering this body,
after entering this body,
my cultivation plummeted.
my cultivation plummeted.
To avoid that powerful enemy,
Upang maiwasan ang makapangyarihang kaaway na iyon,
I disguised myself as an ordinary man
I disguised myself as an ordinary man
and made a living
at gumawa ng isang
with a blacksmith
buhay na may panday
in the city.
in the city.
Over time,
Sa paglipas ng panahon,
I got close to the townspeople,
I got close to the townspeople,
and someone even tried to matchmake for me.
At may sinubukan pa ring matchmake para sa akin.
Eventually,
Eventually,
she became my wife,
Siya ay naging asawa ko, at ang
and that child became my daughter.
anak na iyon ay naging anak ko.
Before I knew it,
Before I knew it,
five years had passed just like that.
Limang taon na ang lumipas na ganyan.
You never thought
You never thought
about going back?
Tungkol sa Pagbabalik?
In the demonic sects, it's all survival of the fittest.
In the demonic sects, it is all survival of the fittest.
Now that I'm weak,
Ngayon na ako ay mahina,
if I returned,
if I returned,
my own fellow sect members would likely kill me.
Ang aking sariling kapwa miyembro ng sekta ay malamang na papatayin ako.
Besides,
Besides,
these hands are better suited to the forge
Ang mga kamay na ito ay mas mahusay na angkop sa forge
than the battlefield.
than the battlefield.
Life is peaceful now.
Ang buhay ay mapayapa ngayon.
Why would I want to go back to a world of endless killing?
Why would I want to go back to a world of endless killing?
Peaceful?
Mapayapa?
The demonic sects have already taken over the eastern region of Yue Kingdom.
The demonic sects have already taken over the eastern region of Yue Kingdom.
How long do you think
Gaano katagal sa tingin mo
this peace will last?
Ang kapayapaan na ito ay tatagal?
Already?
Already?
That can't be. It's far too soon.
Hindi iyon maaaring.  It is far too soon.
You're not an ordinary demonic cultivator.
Hindi ka isang ordinaryong demonyong magsasaka.
Tell me.
Tell me.
Who are you, really?
Sino ka talaga?
No matter who I used to be,
No matter who I used to be,
that part of me is gone now.
that part of me is gone now.
Why press me for answers?
Bakit pindutin ako para sa mga sagot?
Take my advice.
Take my advice.
The Seven Sects will lose.
Mawawala ang pitong sekta.
Make your move early.
Make your move early.
Don't lose your life in vain.
Huwag mawala ang iyong buhay nang walang kabuluhan.
This man knows more than he's letting on.
This man knows more than he is letting on.
I'll have to pry more information out of him.
Kailangan kong mag -pry ng karagdagang impormasyon sa kanya.
Right now, the battle is at a stalemate.
Right now, the battle is at a stalemate.
The Seven Sects are united against the demonic sects,
Ang pitong sekta ay nagkakaisa laban sa mga demonyong sekta,
but talk of victory or defeat
but talk of victory or defeat
seems a little premature.
Mukhang isang maliit na napaaga.
There's a long and bitter history between the Seven Sects
There's a long and bitter history between the Seven Sects
and the Six Demonic Sects.
at ang anim na demonyong sekta.
Cultivators are innately selfish.
Cultivators are innately selfish.
Backstabbing is nothing new.
Ang backstabbing ay walang bago.
The so-called impenetrable alliance of the Seven Sects
The so-called impenetrable alliance of the Seven Sects
has already been
ay lubusang na
thoroughly infiltrated by us.
-infiltrate sa amin.
In fact,
In fact,
Spirit Beast Mountain
Espiritu ng hayop na bundok
is the Beast Taming Sect's spy here.
is the Beast Taming Sect's spy here.
The Six Demonic Sects
Ang anim na demonyong sekta
will win this battle.
will win this battle.
Spirit Beast Mountain pretended to defect,
Nagpapanggap ang Espiritu ng Hayop na Bundok na may depekto,
then wiped out two Core Formation Stage cultivators from the demonic sects.
then wiped out two Core Formation Stage cultivators from the demonic sects.
Everyone in the Seven Sects knows that story.
Alam ng lahat sa pitong sekta ang kwentong iyon.
This whole "spy" thing
This whole "spy" thing
was just a lie to fool the ignorant.
ay kasinungalingan lamang upang lokohin ang ignorante.
Without those Core Formation cultivators "dying,"
Kung wala ang mga pangunahing tagapagtaguyod ng pagbuo na "namamatay,"
would the Seven Sects have so easily trusted us?
would the Seven Sects have so easily trusted us?
Besides,
Bukod sa,
do you genuinely believe the ones who died
do you genuinely believe the ones who died
were actually Core Formation cultivators?
were actually Core Formation cultivators?
As far as I know,
Sa pagkakaalam ko,
the Six Demonic Sects have
the Six Demonic Sects have
at least three secret techniques that forcefully boost
Hindi bababa sa tatlong lihim na pamamaraan na malakas na mapalakas
a Foundation Establishment cultivator to appear
ang isang nagtatanim ng pagtatatag ng pundasyon na lilitaw
as a Core Formation one.
as a Core Formation one.
The effect doesn't last long,
Ang epekto ay hindi magtatagal,
but long enough to deceive your people.
but long enough to deceive your people.
Give me one reason not to kill you.
Bigyan mo ako ng isang dahilan na hindi ka papatayin.
If you spare me,
If you spare me,
I'll tell you where I've been hiding.
Sasabihin ko sa iyo kung saan ako nagtatago.
All the artifacts and gems there
All the artifacts and gems there
will be yours.
magiging iyo.
They are of no use
They are of no use
to this body
sa katawan na ito
anyway.
anyway.
You expect me to believe your generosity?
Inaasahan mong maniwala ako sa iyong kabutihang -loob?
You're calculating, that's for sure.
You are calculating, that is for sure.
Fine.
Fine.
Given how things have turned out,
Given how things have turned out,
I'll hand over the artifacts and gems
Ibibigay ko ang mga artifact at hiyas
as well as the jade slips and letters
as well as the jade slips and letters
that detail my sect's dealings
Iyon ang detalyeng pakikitungo ng aking sekta
with Spirit Beast Mountain.
with Spirit Beast Mountain.
If what you find
Kung ang nahanap
isn't enough,
mo ay hindi sapat,
go ahead and kill me right here.
go ahead and kill me right here.
I won't complain.
Hindi ako magrereklamo.
But please,
But please,
spare my wife and daughter.
ekstrang asawa ko at anak na babae.
They're mere mortals.
They are mere mortals.
They've done nothing wrong.
Wala silang nagawa.
Something about this feels off.
Something about this feels off.
Better to be cautious.
Mas mahusay na maging maingat.
Where can I find the items?
Where can I find the items?
Right here.
Dito mismo.
If you're not convinced,
Kung hindi ka kumbinsido,
I'll go with you.
I will go with you.
You seem impatient.
Parang walang tiyaga ka.
You'll have to wait right here until I get back.
You will have to wait right here until I get back.
Such a crude trap.
Ang nasabing isang bitag na bitag.
You think too little of me.
You think too little of me.
Go.
Pumunta ka na
What's…
What's…
It's fast.
Mabilis ito.
It even blocked off my escape.
It even blocked off my escape.
[Goldenback Demon Mantis]
[Goldenback Demon Mantis]
What kind of demon beast is this?
What kind of demon beast is this?
It even flies.
Lumipad pa ito.
Even if it's not Level 5,
Even if it is not Level 5,
it's at least peak Level 4.
Ito ay hindi bababa sa antas ng rurok 4.
That's enough to hold its own against a Core Formation cultivator.
That is enough to hold its own against a Core Formation cultivator.
My Mother-Child Blades!
Ang mga blades ng aking ina-anak!
This loss
This loss
cuts deep.
Malalim ang pagputol.
If this keeps up,
If this keeps up,
it's only a matter of time before I get caught.
Ilang oras lang bago ako mahuli.
This better work.
This better work.
That was too close.
Iyon ay masyadong malapit.
I nearly lost my life back there.
I nearly lost my life back there.
This place isn't far from Jiayuan City.
Ang lugar na ito ay hindi malayo sa lungsod ng Jiayuan.
A demon beast that strong
A demon beast that strong
can't be wild.
Hindi maaaring maging ligaw.
It probably belongs
It probably belongs
to that man from the Beast Taming Sect.
sa taong iyon mula sa sekta ng hayop na hayop.
No Foundation Establishment cultivator
No Foundation Establishment cultivator
could control a creature like this.
maaaring makontrol ang isang nilalang na tulad nito.
Could that guy
Could that guy
have been a Core Formation cultivator?
ay naging isang pangunahing tagatanim ng pagbuo?
Curses.
Curses.
The pouch I risked everything to retrieve
Ang pouch ay pinanganib ko ang lahat upang makuha
is empty.
is empty.
All right.
Sige.
So you set me up.
So you set me up.
Don't blame me for what happens next.
Huwag mo akong sisihin sa susunod na mangyayari.
You're still alive.
You are still alive.
That pill has a strange effect.
Ang tableta na iyon ay may kakaibang epekto.
It pushed his power straight up to Mid Foundation Stage.
It pushed his power straight up to Mid Foundation Stage.
Blood Spirit Drill!
Dugo ng Dugo ng Dugo!
The Verdant Sword.
The Verdant Sword.
That's a Core Formation Stage artifact.
Iyon ay isang artifact na yugto ng pagbuo.
A Spirit Companion,
A Spirit Companion,
a Core Formation Stage artifact,
Isang artifact na yugto ng pagbuo ng pangunahing,
and a Golden Core.
and a Golden Core.
This man was definitely
Ang taong ito ay tiyak na isang
a Core Formation Stage cultivator.
Core Formation Stage Cultivator.
Even…
Even…
Even the Goldenback Demon Mantis couldn't kill you.
Kahit na ang Goldenback Demon Mantis ay hindi ka maaaring pumatay sa iyo.
Being bested by you today
Being bested by you today
is no dishonor…
ay walang kahiya -hiya...
You are indeed a Core Formation cultivator.
You are indeed a Core Formation cultivator.
Any last words?
Anumang mga huling salita?
Father!
Father!
Dear!
Mahal!
What happened to you?
What happened to you?
They…
Sila…
They had nothing to do with this.
They had nothing to do with this.
Please…
Mangyaring…
Please do not harm them…
Please do not harm them…
Was I the one who harmed them?
Ako ba ang puminsala sa kanila?
You should know this already.
You should know this already.
Your body is steeped in dark aura.
Ang iyong katawan ay matarik sa madilim na aura.
Just being near you
Just being near you
drains their life force.
pinatuyo ang kanilang lakas sa buhay.
They don't have much time left.
They do not have much time left.
You think I don't know that?
Sa palagay mo hindi ko alam iyon?
All the cultivation I have left
All the cultivation I have left
is sealed inside this broken core.
ay selyadong sa loob ng sirang core na ito.
Once they take it,
Once they take it,
it will restore their vitality
Ibabalik nito ang kanilang sigla
and extend their lives.
and extend their lives.
You knew this day would come.
Alam mo na darating ang araw na ito.
Father…
Father…
I spent half my life committing evil,
Ginugol ko ang kalahati ng aking buhay na gumawa ng kasamaan,
and now the last thing I do
and now the last thing I do
is for two mortals…
ay para sa dalawang mortal...
Dear…
Dear…
Father,
Ama, mangyaring huwag mamatay.
The things I promised
The things I promised
are on my real body
ay nasa totoong katawan ko
in the cave.
in the cave.
I wasn't lying.
Hindi ako nagsisinungaling.
The messages with Spirit Beast Mountain,
The messages with Spirit Beast Mountain,
and my identity token,
At ang aking token ng pagkakakilanlan,
will prove everything.
will prove everything.
I leave the rest to you.
Iniwan ko ang natitira sa iyo.
Thank you…
Salamat...
When you wake,
When you wake,
forget all of this…
Kalimutan ang lahat ng ito...
Cultivator,
Cultivator,
in your world,
sa iyong mundo,
what's genuine
what is genuine
and what's forged?
At ano ang huwad?
Now,
Now,
it's time to figure out how to handle that demon beast.
Panahon na upang malaman kung paano mahawakan ang hayop na demonyo.
The Five Phases Reversing Array
The Five Phases Reversing Array
has never let me down.
ay hindi ako pinabayaan.
This has to be the remains of that Beast Taming Sect cultivator.
This has to be the remains of that Beast Taming Sect cultivator.
With wounds like those,
May mga sugat tulad ng mga iyon,
it's no surprise he didn't even have time to retrieve his mystic pouch.
it is no surprise he didn't even have time to retrieve his mystic pouch.
This is a Spirit Companion Beast Egg.
Ito ay isang espiritu ng hayop na hayop na itlog.
These insects are unbelievably tough.
These insects are unbelievably tough.
The Beast Taming Sect
Ang sekta ng hayop
does have some skill.
does have some skill.
"Compendium of Mystical Insects."
"Compendium ng Mystical Insect."
Blood Jade Spider,
Blood Jade Spider,
ranked 108.
ranggo ng 108.
Goldenback Demon Mantis, ranked 73.
Goldenback Demon Mantis, ranked 73.
Gold-devouring Bug,
Bug-devouring bug,
ranked 12.
ranked 12.
Seriously?
Seryoso?
You're kidding.
You are kidding.
That Goldenback Demon Mantis
Ang gintong mantis ng Goldenback na iyon
ranks just 73?
ranks just 73?
"A Guide to Breeding and Commanding Them."
"Isang gabay sa pag -aanak at pag -uutos sa kanila."
Never mind.
Never mind.
I'll study this when I have the time.
Pag -aaralan ko ito kapag may oras ako.
Found it.
Found it.
Correspondence between Spirit Beast Mountain and the Beast Taming Sect.
Pagsusulat sa pagitan ng Spirit Beast Mountain at ang sekta ng hayop na Taming.
Your master is dead.
Your master is dead.
You can rest now.
Maaari kang magpahinga ngayon.
The damage you caused to my artifact
The damage you caused to my artifact
will be repaid using your materials.
babayaran gamit ang iyong mga materyales.
Qu Hun,
Qu Hun,
I'll craft you a proper armor with this.
Gagawin kita ng isang tamang sandata kasama nito.
The matter's wrapped up.
The matter's wrapped up.
It's time to report back.
Panahon na upang mag -ulat pabalik.
No matter the outcome,
No matter the outcome,
I have done my part.
Nagawa ko na ang bahagi ko.
Elder Han rose to fame in a single battle.
Si Elder Han ay tumaas sa katanyagan sa isang solong labanan.
I'm nowhere near that level.
I am nowhere near that level.
Even with the stalemate at Golden Drum Plains,
Kahit na sa stalemate sa Golden Drum
you still hold everything together.
Plains, pinagsama mo pa rin ang lahat.
I respect that.
I respect that.
At this point,
Sa puntong ito, ang pitong sekta
the Seven Sects are on the verge of destruction.
ay nasa gilid ng pagkawasak.
No one can afford to sit this out.
No one can afford to sit this out.
Watching our disciples storm the battlefield one after another,
Pinapanood ang aming mga alagad na bumagsak sa
how could an old man like me
larangan ng digmaan, paano ang isang matandang tulad ko
just stand aside?
just stand aside?
Even if not for myself,
Kahit na hindi para sa aking sarili,
I must fight
I must fight for
for all my disciples.
all my disciples.
Everyone!
Lahat!
Look who just showed up!
Look who just showed up!
No one going to give me a proper welcome?
Walang magbibigay sa akin ng tamang maligayang pagdating?
Shameless.
Shameless.
You show up late
Lumitaw ka ng huli at inaasahan
and expect a grand entrance?
ang isang engrandeng pasukan?
I'm late?
I am late?
My apologies.
Humihingi ako ng paumanhin.
Han,
Han,
when did you arrive?
Kailan ka dumating?
Just got here myself.
Just got here myself.
See? We're about the same.
Kita?  We are about the same.
Enough.
Sapat na.
I'm hungry
I am hungry and thirsty.
Bring out
Ilabas
the best pastries
the best pastries from
from Yellow Maple Valley.
Yellow Maple Valley.
No pastries,
Walang pastry,
but plenty of sand.
but plenty of sand.
Want some?
Gusto mo ng ilan?
Enough banter.
Enough banter.
Let's get down to business.
Bumaba tayo sa negosyo.
Take out
Take out
your upgraded
Ang iyong na -upgrade
Level 4 demon beast mahjong set.
Level 4 demon beast mahjong set.
Waging war every day
Ang Waging War araw
gets tedious.
-araw ay nakakapagod.
We need a way to relieve some tension.
We need a way to relieve some tension.
Now that's more like it.
Ngayon ay mas katulad ito.
Put that away.
Put that away.
Fu Yunzi,
Fu Yunzi,
stop turning up
stop turning up
just to eat and play.
just to eat and play.
We called you here for a serious matter.
Tinawagan ka namin dito para sa isang seryosong bagay.
That's right.
That is right.
Hongfu, please speak.
Hongfu, mangyaring magsalita.
Our scouts on the front lines
Ang aming mga scout sa mga linya ng harap
have observed signs that the demonic sects may launch
have observed signs that the demonic sects may
an offensive at the start of next month.
launch an offensive at the start of next month.
Huayuan and I are planning to send a group
Nagpaplano kami ni Huayuan na magpadala ng isang pangkat
to strike their rear lines.
to strike their rear lines.
Hit them where they least expect it?
Pindutin ang mga ito kung saan hindi nila ito inaasahan?
Hongfu,
Hongfu,
that's a brilliant strategy!
Iyon ay isang napakatalino na diskarte!
How about
How about we make a wager
on the outcome?
sa kinalabasan?
You want to bet on this, too?
You want to bet on this, too?
What are you betting on, success or failure?
Ano ang pustahan mo, tagumpay o pagkabigo?
Success, of course.
Success, of course.
And the rest of us?
At ang natitira sa atin?
Failure.
Failure.
Get out of here!
Lumabas ka rito!
Getting out of here…
Getting out of here…
Dear Master,
Mahal na Guro,
this is Han Li, your disciple,
this is Han Li, your disciple,
sending my respects.
nagpapadala ng respeto ko.
I have returned
I have returned
to the valley to cultivate in seclusion.
sa lambak upang linangin sa pag -iisa.
All is well within the valley.
All is well within the valley.
My thoughts are with you
Ang aking saloobin ay kasama mo
and you alone.
and you alone.
The situation at the front remains uncertain.
Ang sitwasyon sa harap ay nananatiling hindi sigurado.
On my journey back,
On my journey back,
I uncovered evidence of collusion
Natuklasan ko ang katibayan ng pagbangga
between Spirit Beast Mountain
between Spirit Beast Mountain
and the Beast Taming Sect.
at ang sekta ng hayop na taming.
I have submitted
I have submitted
this proof to the Sect Master.
Ang patunay na ito sa Sect Master.
For the sake of morale and caution,
For the sake of morale and caution,
the Sect Master
ang sekta master
has chosen to keep this matter
has chosen to keep this matter
undisclosed.
hindi natukoy.
I fear it may affect
I fear it may affect
the front lines
the front lines
and place you and the other mentors in danger.
At ilagay ka at ang iba pang mga mentor sa panganib.
Though it breaks protocol,
Though it breaks protocol,
I felt compelled
Napilit akong sumulat.
May you remain vigilant.
May you remain vigilant.
I have done all I can from afar.
Nagawa ko na ang lahat ng makakaya ko mula sa malayo.
Master, may this message
Master, may this message
reach you
Abutin ka
in time
in time
to avert disaster.
upang maiwasan ang sakuna.
The great war approaches.
The great war approaches.
You must keep yourself safe too.
Dapat mong panatilihing ligtas din ang iyong sarili.
The Goldenback Demon Mantis armor…
The Goldenback Demon Mantis armor…
is too small.
ay masyadong maliit.
They've already hatched.
They've already hatched.
And they eat
At kumakain sila
so much.
so much.
I suppose
Akala ko
not all cultivators can afford to keep Spirit Companions.
not all cultivators can afford to keep Spirit Companions.
I should find time
Dapat akong makahanap ng oras
to visit the Herbs Garden.
to visit the Herbs Garden.
Get in.
Pumasok.
Master replied already?
Master replied already?
Do you remember our promise
Naaalala mo ba ang aming
to admire the flowers
pangako na humanga sa mga bulaklak
beneath Baili Mountain?
beneath Baili Mountain?
Maybe you can go on my behalf?
Siguro maaari kang pumunta sa aking ngalan?
Senior Chen.
Senior Chen.
When I was young,
Noong bata pa ako,
my mother often brought me here
my mother often brought me here
to gather wild chrysanthemums.
upang mangalap ng mga ligaw na chrysanthemums.
To her,
To her,
no flower was more beautiful
Walang bulaklak na mas maganda
than these wild chrysanthemums.
than these wild chrysanthemums.
But after she passed away
Ngunit pagkatapos niyang lumipas
a few years ago,
a few years ago,
I stopped coming.
Huminto ako sa darating.
Senior,
Senior,
please accept my condolences.
Mangyaring tanggapin ang aking pakikiramay.
It's all right.
It is all right.
To her,
Sa kanya,
it might have been a release from the burdens she carried.
it might have been a release from the burdens she carried.
She was also married into the Chen family through a political alliance.
Siya rin ay ikinasal sa pamilyang Chen sa pamamagitan ng isang alyansa sa politika.
Before their wedding,
Before their wedding,
she and my father had never met.
Siya at ang aking ama ay hindi pa nagkakilala.
After marriage, they treated each other with respect,
After marriage, they treated each other with respect,
but I know
Ngunit alam ko
they never truly opened up to one another.
they never truly opened up to one another.
Do you think
Sa tingin mo ba
it's unbecoming for me as a cultivator
it is unbecoming for me as a cultivator
to always be caught up
Upang laging mahuli
in matters of love?
in matters of love?
Not at all.
Hindi naman.
Sadly, you don't understand.
Sadly, you do not understand.
For women born into noble families,
Para sa mga babaeng ipinanganak sa mga marangal na pamilya,
from the day we are born,
from the day we are born,
our lives
ang ating buhay
no longer belong to ourselves.
no longer belong to ourselves.
We train day after day,
Nagsasanay kami araw -araw,
bringing benefits to our clans.
bringing benefits to our clans.
Maybe, just maybe, 1 prodigy out of 10,000
Siguro, marahil, 1 prodigy sa 10,000
might earn the trust of the Seven Sects within 100 years
might earn the trust of the Seven Sects within 100 years
and gain the right to choose their fate.
at makuha ang karapatang pumili ng kanilang kapalaran.
But most of them
But most of them
end up like me.
magtapos na tulad ko.
You're being too modest.
You are being too modest.
Since you entered the valley,
Mula nang pumasok ka sa lambak,
your diligence
your diligence
and calmness in all matters
at katahimikan sa lahat ng bagay
have surely not gone unnoticed by anyone.
have surely not gone unnoticed by anyone.
Even if you're not a prodigy,
Kahit na hindi ka isang prodigy,
you're well beyond
you are well beyond
the average clan disciple.
the average clan disciple.
You know that's not the answer I wanted to hear.
Alam mo na hindi iyon ang sagot na nais kong marinig.
The reason I asked to see you today
The reason I asked to see you today
is
ay
that I may soon
that I may soon
be married.
ikakasal.
The groom is the son of the Qi family.
The groom is the son of the Qi family.
We've never met,
Hindi pa kami nagkakilala,
but I've heard
but I have heard
he's a man of decent character.
Siya ay isang tao ng disenteng pagkatao.
War is raging across the land,
War is raging across the
and no one is safe.
land, and no one is safe.
If the Chen family can form an alliance with them
Kung ang pamilyang Chen ay maaaring bumuo ng isang alyansa
and find shelter from the chaos,
sa kanila at makahanap ng kanlungan mula sa kaguluhan,
then…
then…
When we were in the Imperial Capital,
Noong nasa kapital na ito ng imperyal,
I saw Weiniang and Senior Liu together.
I saw Weiniang and Senior Liu together.
I found myself envying them.
Natagpuan ko ang aking sarili na naiinggit sa kanila.
At least they met
At least they met
and fell in love.
and fell in love.
Even if they were separated by life and death,
Kahit na sila ay pinaghiwalay ng buhay at kamatayan,
it was still better
it was still better
than living an entire life trapped,
kaysa sa pamumuhay ng isang buong buhay na nakulong,
never free,
never free,
and dying with regrets.
at namamatay na may panghihinayang.
Why?
Why?
Why should I be forced
Bakit ako pipilitin na magpakasal
to marry someone I've never met?
sa isang taong hindi ko pa nakilala?
Why should I be passed around
Why should I be passed
like some commodity,
around like some commodity,
today to the Lu family, tomorrow to the Qi family?
Ngayon sa pamilyang LU, bukas sa pamilyang Qi?
Why should the fate of the entire clan
Why should the fate of the entire clan
be placed on the shoulders of a single woman?
mailagay sa balikat ng isang solong babae?
No one has ever asked what I want.
No one has ever asked what I want.
Not once.
Hindi minsan.
Can I lean on you, just for a moment?
Can I lean on you, just for a moment?
Han,
Han,
I know you're different.
I know you are different.
Are you planning something?
May pinaplano ka ba?
Can you take me away from here?
Can you take me away from here?
Just take me away.
Dalhin mo lang ako.
Anywhere will do,
Anywhere will do, so long…
so long as it's a place where I can be free.
Hangga't ito ay isang lugar kung saan maaari akong malaya.
I've done all of this
I have done all of this
and yet
At pa
you still hold back.
you still hold back.
You're making me feel quite embarrassed.
Pinahihiya mo ako.
Do you
Do you
already have someone in your heart?
Mayroon na bang isang tao sa iyong puso?
Senior,
Senior,
please don't tease me like that.
Mangyaring huwag mo akong panunukso ng ganyan.
♪Time and time again, it never changes...♪
♪Time and time again, it never changes...♪
Thank you for all the times
Salamat sa lahat ng oras
you've saved me.
you have saved me.
♪Taking away my emptiness...♪
♪ Pag -alis ng aking kawalan ng laman... ♪
I have nothing worthy to give in return,
I have nothing worthy to give in return,
but I am skilled with embroidery.
Ngunit bihasa ako sa pagbuburda.
I made a robe for you.
I made a robe for you.
Try it on and see if it fits.
Subukan ito at tingnan kung umaangkop ito.
You're a Late Foundation Stage cultivator now.
Ikaw ay isang late foundation stage cultivator ngayon.
You ought to look the part.
You ought to look the part.
It's just a gift.
Ito ay isang regalo lamang.
If you refuse,
If you refuse,
I'll have to throw it away.
Kailangan kong itapon ito.
Thank you, Senior.
Thank you, Senior.
♪We promised to enter the dream together...♪
♪ Nangako kaming ipasok ang pangarap na magkasama... ♪
It has purification and water-repelling arrays
It has purification and water-repelling arrays
woven into it.
pinagtagpi sa loob nito.
You put a lot of thought into it.
You put a lot of thought into it.
♪Let time sweep through...♪
♪ Hayaan ang oras na magwalis sa... ♪
Senior,
Senior,
I have some beauty-enhancing pills here.
Mayroon akong ilang mga tabletas na nagpapahusay ng kagandahan dito.
I made them myself.
I made them myself.
Please,
Mangyaring,
accept them.
accept them.
As long as they're not anything weird.
Hangga't hindi sila kakaiba.
♪It's as if we've never left each other♪
♪It is as if we've never left each other♪
♪Searching and searching...♪
♪ Paghahanap at Paghahanap... ♪
It's getting late.
It is getting late.
It's time for me to leave the valley.
Panahon na para umalis ako sa lambak.
Han,
Han,
until we meet again.
Hanggang sa magkita ulit tayo.
Take care,
Take care,
Senior.
Senior.
♪Let time sweep through♪
♪Let time sweep through♪
♪The mountains♪
♪ Ang mga bundok ♪
♪Thoughts turn...♪
♪Thoughts turn...♪
No matter what happens,
Kahit anong mangyari,
I hope you find the freedom
I hope you find the freedom
you seek.
Humahanap ka.
♪If our heart connects♪
♪If our heart connects♪
♪It's as if we've never left each other♪
♪ Ito ay parang hindi pa namin iniwan ang bawat isa ♪
♪Searching and searching♪
♪Searching and searching♪
♪For your whereabouts♪
♪ Para sa iyong kinaroroonan ♪
♪Shards of dreams inside a dream♪
♪Shards of dreams inside a dream♪
♪A pale moon falls into mirrored skies♪
♪ Ang isang maputlang buwan ay nahuhulog sa mirrored kalangitan ♪
♪Years slipped by as I lingered on♪
♪Years slipped by as I lingered on♪
♪Old scenes rise again♪
♪ Tumataas muli ang mga lumang eksena ♪
♪Too hard to forget♪
♪ masyadong mahirap kalimutan ♪
♪Easier just to miss♪
♪Easier just to miss♪
♪They say the past fades like smoke♪
♪ Sinasabi nila ang nakaraan na nawawala tulad ng usok ♪
♪But looking back still stirs the ache♪
♪But looking back still stirs the ache♪
♪This noisy world, this lonely page♪
♪ Ang maingay na mundo na ito, ang malungkot na pahina na ito
♪Swept away by time♪
♪Swept away by time♪
♪Eyes once looked far♪
♪ Ang mga mata ay minsan ay tumingin sa malayo ♪
♪Now lost in the shift♪
♪Now lost in the shift♪
♪Autumn winds stir♪
♪ Ang hangin ng taglagas ay gumalaw ♪
♪Smoke curls once more♪
♪Smoke curls once more♪
♪Like clouds on the edge of sky♪
♪ Tulad ng mga ulap sa gilid ng kalangitan ♪
♪Returning to my eyes♪
♪Returning to my eyes♪
♪Looking back from the mountaintop♪
♪ Tumingin sa likod mula sa Mountaintop ♪
♪Time lost its name♪
♪Time lost its name♪
♪Was it yesterday♪
♪ Ito ba kahapon ♪
♪Or tomorrow?♪
♪Or tomorrow?♪
♪The world has changed♪
♪ Ang mundo ay nagbago ♪
♪Beyond recall♪
♪Beyond recall♪
♪Time will fade♪
♪ Ang oras ay mawawala ♪
♪All the words ever spoken♪
♪All the words ever spoken♪
♪Only this longing remains♪
♪ Ang pananabik na ito ay nananatili ♪
♪Crossing centuries and days♪
♪Crossing centuries and days♪
♪In a fleeting moment we call eternity♪
♪ Sa isang mabilis na sandali na tinatawag nating kawalang -hanggan ♪
♪In a fleeting moment called eternity♪
♪In a fleeting moment called eternity♪